Guide to the Acme Company Gadgetry Division records, 1949-1966
Random University Library
Acme Company Gadgetry Division records
1949 1966
MC 123
Acme Company Gadgetry Division
7 archival boxes
3.5 linear feet
Random University Archives and Special Collections
Serving a variety of Looney Toon needs, the Gadgetry Division of the Acme Company began production of its various products in the 1940s. Primarily geared toward the capture of various elusive characters that tormented their opponents, Acme sought to provide the necessary equipment for resolution of many chases. Prominent customers include Elmer Fudd, Sylvester the Cat, Pepe Le Pew, and most notably Wile E. Coyote, who became official product test representative for the company. Mr. Coyote was the Division’s most prolific customer, despite his difficulties in execution of the products. He had a standing order for dynamite and received a catalog of their new products quarterly. Mr. Coyote stopped purchasing products from the Gadgetry Division in 1966 and subsequently disappeared from public life. Without its chief customer and record sales of the Gadgetry Division, Acme dissolved it as a division that same year.
This collection documents the business generated by the Gadgetry Division of the Acme Company from 1949 to 1966. It includes correspondence, research information on products and on Wile E. Coyote, product testing videos recorded by Wile E. Coyote, and the Division’s catalogs throughout its existence.
Restrictions to Access
This collection is open to all coyotes. Some restrictions apply.
The series of Product Design Files is restricted. Permission from the Acme Company is required.
Acquisitions Information
The Acme Company Archives was transferred to the Call of the Coyote Library through gift in 2003.
Historical Note
Serving a variety of Looney Toon needs, the Gadgetry Division of the Acme Company began production of its various products in the 1940s. Primarily geared toward the capture of various elusive characters that tormented their opponents, Acme sought to provide the necessary equipment for resolution of many chases. While Gadgetry Division products did not succeed in providing the chasers with the appropriate acquisition, they enjoyed an almost two-decade unprecedented sales record for their contraptions. Most failures of products can be attributed to inappropriate use by purchasers in their eagerness to catch their prey.
Prominent customers include Elmer Fudd, Sylvester the Cat, Pepe Le Pew, and most notably Wile E. Coyote, who became official product test representative for the company. The in-depth relationship that grew between this division and its customers accounts for many specialized products. Mr. Coyote was the Division’s most prolific customer, despite his difficulties in execution of the products. He had a standing order for dynamite and received a catalog of their new products quarterly. The Gadgetry Division began supplying Mr. Coyote with all his bird seed needs in 1951 when he made a special request, including several different varieties. Mr. Coyote provided Acme with the appropriate documentation of the use of their products through short films so that they could assess them for mass marketing after making some improvement. Many of the videos demonstrate not the product faultiness, but the lack of adherence by Mr. Coyote to follow directions.
Mr. Coyote stopped purchasing products from the Gadgetry Division in 1966 and subsequently disappeared from public life. Without its chief customer and record sales of the Gadgetry Division, Acme dissolved it as a division that same year. The Road Runner also disappeared in 1966, but has resurfaced as a spokesbird for an internet-provider service. It is rumored that the Road Runner is doing quite well, while Wile E. Coyote has remained elusive since his disappearance.
Scope and Content of the Collection
This collection documents the business generated by the Gadgetry Division of the Acme Company from 1949 to 1966. It includes correspondence, research information on products and on Wile E. Coyote, product testing videos recorded by Wile E. Coyote, and the Division’s catalogs throughout its existence. The correspondence series documents the internal discussions about the creation of the Division, its tumultuous relationship with Mr. Coyote, and a great deal of product research for gadgets made by special request. The testing videos demonstrate the gadgets in use by Wile E. Coyote. These videos demonstrated to the Division that they needed improvements not only in the products themselves but also in the construction of their gadgets. They also document the relationship between Wile E. Coyote and the Road Runner and highlight some other prominent figures in Looney Toon, such as Bugs Bunny. Finally, the Gadget catalogs give a sense of the progress of the Division’s products.
Most of the client files were destroyed in a TNT accident in 1966 and are therefore not represented in the collection. Wile E. Coyote records were kept separately from other customers due to his willingness to test new products for effectiveness.
Arrangment of the Collection
These records are organized into five series: Correspondence, Research, Product Design, Product Testing Videos, and Gadget Catalogs.
Series are organized either chronologically or alphabetically by topic. Original order has been maintained in the Product Design Files Series.
Index Terms
Acme Company Gadgetry Division; Commercial Products Testing; Costume design; Coyote Behavior; Coyote Feeds and feeding; Explosives Accidents Investigation Nevada; Explosives Catalogs; Jones, Chunck 1912-2002; Looney tunes (Firm); New products Design and construction; New products Evaluation; Roadrunner (Fictitious character); Wile E. Coyote (Fictitious character)
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Correspondence, 1949-1966; ½ archival box, about 100 items
  Scope and content:
  The Correspondence series includes correspondence between the Division Head, Chuck Jones, and various customers and Acme officials. It includes early discussion about the creation of the division as well as proposed product lines, requests for special orders, and test results. These files are organized chronologically.
  Arrangement:
  Chronological
  - Correspondence, 1949-1954 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1955-1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, January 1960-April 1960 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, May 1960-September 1960 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, October 1961-January 1963 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, February 1963-1966 (Box 1)
- Research Files, 1 ½ archival box, about 600 items.
  Due to the demands of its customers, the Gadgetry Division maintained research files on a variety of periphery items that they wanted to provide. These files include reprints of research articles, newsclippings, and original manuscripts on various supporting material for the gadget designs.
  Wile E. Coyote was the most prolific customer of the Gadgetry Division. He also served as the chief product tester for the Division and recorded his tests on video. Wile E. Coyote is a predator with enormous intelligence. In addition his stead-fast devotion to catching the Road Runner and occasional tangles with Bugs Bunny provided ample opportunity for the Gadgetry Division to use him as a test-case for their products. It was clear though from the many tests that he documented that he was often too eager to catch his prey than to think clearly about the applications of the gadgets. The Gadgetry Division did a great deal of research on Mr. Coyote and his prey in order to effectively serve his needs and increase their sales.
  Topical
  - Birdseed recipes (Box 1)
  - Explosive devices (Box 1)
  - Roadrunners (Box 2)
  - Rocket capabilities (Box 2)
  - Wile E.Coyote (Box 2)
    - Feeding habits (Box 2)
    - Social habits (Box 2)
    - Mechanical skills (Box 2)
- Product Design Files, 2 archival boxes, about 600 items
  Series includes information on various gadgets designed by the gadgetry division, including design specifications, concept drawings, and mock-ups. Each product had a design file, and these files were preserved in their original order.
  Restricted: This series is restricted. Permission from the Acme Company is required.
  Original order
  - Weapons (Box 3)
    - Catapult (Box 3)
    - Cannon (Box 3)
    - Explosives (Box 3)
      - Dynamite (Box 3)
      - Egg Bomb (Box 3)
      - Kite Bomb (Box 3)
      - Nitroglycerin-filled Carrot (Box 3)
      - TNT (Box 3)
    - Lasso (Box 3)
  - Costumes (Folder 3)
    - Batman (Box 3)
    - Road Runner (Box 3)
    - Rocket Man (Box 3)
  - Vehicles (Folder 3)
    - Fan Powered Skateboard (Box 3)
    - Fan Powered Skates (Box 3)
  - Helicopter (Box 4)
  - Jet Propelled Pogo Stick (Box 4)
  - Rocket (Box 4)
  - Rocket Powered Roller Skates (Box 4)
  - Roller Skates (Box 4)
  - Roller Skis (Box 4)
  - General (Box 4)
    - Burmese Tiger Trap (Box 4)
    - Dehydrated Boulder (Box 4)
    - Fake Railroad Crossing (Box 4)
    - Fake Tunnel (Box 4)
    - Portable Hole (Box 4)
    - Spring-loaded Boxing Gloves (Box 4)
    - Vacuum Cleaner (Box 4)
- Product Testing Video, 1949-1966; 1 ½ archival boxes, 11 items
  Wile E. Coyote was eager to become the tester for the Gadgetry Division, primarily so that he could obtain the newest products created. In accordance with his agreement with the Acme Company, Wile E. Coyote video-taped his use of the gadgets in his natural setting. Due to a great deal of frustration, primarily of his own making, he titled the videos himself. These videos are organized in chronological order and demonstrate the whole variety of products that he tested.
  - Acme.1949.1, Fast and Furry-ous, 1949-09-17 (Box 5)
  - Acme.1952.2, Beep, Beep, 1952-05-24 (Box 5)
  - Acme.1956.1, Gee Whiz-z-z-z, 1956-05-05 (Box 5)
  - Acme.1958.3, Hip, Hip-HuRoad Runnery!, 1958-12-06 (Box 5)
  - Acme.1960.1, Fastest with the Mostest, 1960-01-09 (Box 5)
  - Acme.1960.3, Hopalong Casualty, 1960-10-08 (Box 5)
  - Acme.1965.2, Rushing Roulette, 1965-07-31 (Box 5)
  - Acme.1965.9, Chaser On the Rocks, 1965-12-25 (Box 6)
  - Acme.1966.1, Shot and Bothered, 1966-01-08 (Box 6)
  - Acme.1966.3, Clippety Clobbered, 1966-03-26 (Box 6)
  - Acme.1966.4, Sugar and Spies, 1966-11-05 (Box 6)
- Gadget Catalogs, 1953/1966; 1 ½ archival boxes, 14 items
  In 1953, the Gadgetry Division began to produce catalogs of their products for their customers. The catalogs document the various products as they were offered for purchase and specifications that Wile E. Coyote would often ignore when he tested them. They document the overall product line for each of the 13 years that they were produced. This series contains all the catalogs produced and is organized in chronological order.
  - Gadget Catalogs, 1953-1957 (Box 6)
  - Gadget Catalogs, 1958-1966 (Box 7)